Guide to the Louisa E. Rhine Papers, 1890-1983 RL.01083
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Louisa E. Rhine papers
1890-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rhine, Louisa E., 1891-1983
RL.01083
5 Linear Feet
3,800 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The papers of Louisa E. Rhine, parapsychologist, author, and wife of Joseph Banks Rhine, were acquired by the Rubenstein Library by gift, in 1985 and 1987.
Biographical Note
Louisa E. Rhine
1891, Nov. 9 Born, Louisa Ella Weckesser, on an island in the Niagara River, New York State.
1919 Bachelor of Science in botany, University of Chicago.
1920 Married Joseph Banks Rhine.
1921 Master of Science in botany, University of Chicago.
1923 Earned Ph.D. in botany, University of Chicago.
1923-24 Research fellow in plant physiology at the Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research in Yonkers, N.Y.
1924-26 Taught Latin at West Virginia University, Morgantown.
1927 Moved to Durham, N.C.
1930-48 Involved in raising her family and civic affairs.
1948 Began active research at the Duke University Parapsychology Laboratory.
1948-83 Research resulted in the publication of 18 scientific reports in the Journal of Parapsychology and 6 books.
1961 Published Hidden Channels of the Mind.
1980 President of the British Society for Psychical Research.
1983, Mar. 17 Died, Durham, N.C.
1983 Something Hidden, detailing the history of J.B. Rhine's research, published posthumously.
Joseph Banks Rhine
1895, Sept. 29 Born, Waterloo, Juniata County, Pennsylvania.
ca. 1915-1917 Attended Ohio Northern University and the College of Wooster as a preministerial student.
1919 Discharged from the U.S. Marine Corps.
1920 Married Louisa Ella Weckesser.
1922 Bachelor of Science in botany, University of Chicago.
1923 Master of Science in botany, University of Chicago.
1923-24 Research fellow in plant physiology at the Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research, Yonkers, New York.
1924-26 Taught plant physiology, West Virginia University in Morgantown.
1925 Ph.D. in botany, University of Chicago.
1926-27 Worked with Dr. Franklin Prince at the Boston Society for Psychical Research.
1927 Came to Duke University to work with Dr. William McDougall, who had just been named head of the Psychology Dept.
1928 Offered an instructorship in philosophy and psychology at Duke with understanding he could do psychical research as well.
1930 Under sponsorship of McDougall, founded Parapsychology Laboratory which at first was part of Duke Psychology Department.
1934 Published Extra-Sensory Perception.
ca. 1935 Laboratory was set apart from the Dept. of Psychology, given some financial support and became known as the Parapsychology Laboratory of Duke University.
1937 Launched the Journal of Parapsychology.
1962 Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man was established under Rhine's guidance.
1965 Retired from Duke and the Duke Parapsychology Laboratory was transferred into the Institute of Parapsychology under the sponsorship of the Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man.
1980, Feb. 20 Died, Hillsborough, N.C.
Collection Overview
The papers of Louisa E. Rhine span the years 1890 to 1983 and include journals, correspondence, writings, genealogical papers, notebooks, pictures, and miscellaneous papers relating principally to her work and research with her husband J.B. Rhine in the field of parapsychology, including the impact of this work on their personal and professional lives.
This impact is shown in Louisa Rhine's journals (1903-1982). The journal entries while not routinely made are nevertheless often lengthy, descriptive, and self-revealing. They document her school days at the University of Chicago, and her courtship, marriage, and relationship with J.B. Rhine. Parts of four journals describe their struggle to understand and to formulate a personal religious philosophy. Others describe their family life and incidents relating to the rearing of their four children. Their work in the Parapsychology Laboratory at Duke, as well as the Laboratory's relationship with the Duke administration are described. The journals include passages from some of J.B. Rhine's letters, interspersed with notes relating to some of Louisa Rhine's studies. Another journal includes excerpts from the other journals.
Correspondence forms the bulk of the collection, and is divided into four categories: personal, special, parapsychological, and business. The most voluminous is personal correspondence primarily from two of the Rhine's children, Sara (Rhine) Feather and Rosemary Rhine. Also included, however, are letters from other family members and friends.
The special correspondence consists of selected correspondence files arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name. The correspondents include: Ella (Long) Weckesser, Louisa Rhine's mother; Sylvia (Weckesser) Newcombe and Miriam (Weckesser) Whaley, sisters of Louisa Rhine; and Barry S. Siegal and William R. Birge, friends of the Rhines, who were officers during World War II.
The parapsychology correspondence includes letters from people in the United States and other countries who wrote to Louisa Rhine relating psychic phenomena either they or someone they knew had experienced. Some of these experiences were reported by Dr. Rhine in her publications.
Business correspondence is chiefly from other scientists in the field of psychical research, information relating to the work and funding of the Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man, and information concerning the publication and translation of some of Louisa Rhine's works.
The personal and business correspondence, reflects the Rhine's concerns about how psychical research would be carried out in the future. They wanted to make sure that an accurate accounting of the work that had begun at Duke under J.B. Rhine's guidance be told. To that end, Louisa Rhine worked during the last years of her life to finish the work recounting as she said J.B.'s attempt to find the 'something lost behind the ranges.' Her efforts resulted in Something Hidden which was published posthumously in 1983.
The business correspondence also describes the strained relationship between Duke University and the Rhines' work both at the Parapsychology Laboratory, when it was officially a part of Duke University, and later when the Laboratory was transferred into the Institute of Parapsychology under the auspices of the Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man.
The writings series contains both parapsychological and other works. The parapsychological writings include a chronological listing of J.B. and Louisa Rhine's works and of critiques and reviews of works by and about them. Also included is information about the Anpsi Project (psychic abilities in animals); miscellaneous notes kept by Louisa and J.B. Rhine; an index to articles in the Journal of Parapsychology (1937-1967); transcripts of interviews with J.B. Rhine; miscellaneous speeches, lectures, and articles relating to the work of the Rhines and others in the parapsychology field; and articles and memorials to honor J.B. Rhine after his death.
Other writings include short stories and poetry by Louisa and J.B. Rhine; anecdotes relating to the Rhines and their children; and attempts by the Rhines to write a work about Our Life Together. There are some fragments of short stories by Louisa Rhine, some giving the author's name as Louise Long a pseudonym adopted when they lived in Massachusetts. One of them "In the Crucible of Life" is apparently a true story about Louisa and J.B. Rhine, although their names have been changed in the story. A note in this section by the Rhine's daughter, Sara (Rhine) Feather (denoted by SRF) tells something about her mother's writings.
Related Material
The Papers of Louisa E. Rhine are related to the records of the Parapsychology Laboratory also held by the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Records of the Parapsychology Laboratory, 1919-1984 250,000 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women -- Diaries; Psychial research; Women scientists; Rhine, J. B. (Joseph Banks), 1895-1980; Rhine family; Weckesser family; Duke University. Parapsychology Laboratory; Long family; Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man.
- Journals, 1903-1982 and undated, 1 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Louisa Rhine's journals overlap each other in terms of the time period covered; two are undated. There are gaps from one to several years in the entries.
  Arrangement note
  - 1903-1916, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 1918-1926, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 1936-1971, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 1942-1957, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 1982, undated and excerpts, 1 folder (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1890-1983 and undated, 8 boxes
  Divided into four subseries: personal, special, parapsychological, and business. The personal correspondence is primarily from the Rhines' children, but also includes letters from other family members and friends. It is arranged chronologically. The special correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name and chronologically within those files. Correspondents' letters in the parapsychological category are divided into two sub-categories: 1) case studies, arranged by the correspondents' last name and 2) miscellany, arranged chronologically. The business correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Personal,1890-1983, undated
    - 1919, Oct.-1950, July, 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1950, Aug.-1955, Dec., 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1956, Jan.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1957, Jan.-July, 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1957, Aug.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1958, Jan.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 3)
    - 1959, Jan.-1974, Dec., 1 folder (Box 3)
    - 1975, Jan.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 3)
    - 1976, Jan.-Nov., 1 folder (Box 3)
    - 1976, Dec., 1 folder (Box 3)
    - 1977, Jan.-1979, Apr., 1 folder (Box 4)
    - 1979, May-Dec., 1 folder (Box 4)
    - 1980, Jan.-Apr., 1 folder (Box 4)
    - 1980, May-Sept., 1 folder (Box 4)
    - 1980, Oct.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 5)
    - 1981, Jan.-Mar., 1 folder (Box 5)
    - 1981, Apr.-Aug., 1 folder (Box 5)
    - 1981, Sept.-Nov., 1 folder (Box 5)
    - 1981, Dec, 1 folder (Box 5)
    - 1982, Jan.-Mar., 1 folder (Box 6)
    - 1982, Apr.-June, 1 folder (Box 6)
    - 1982, July-Sept., 1 folder (Box 6)
    - 1982, Oct.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 6)
    - 1983, Jan.-Dec., 1 folder (Box 6)
    - Undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Special,1890-1982
    - Birge, William R. (Bill) 1942, July-1945, Dec., 1 folder (Box 8)
    - Newcombe, Sylvia (Weckesser) 1926, Sept.-1982, Dec., 1 folder (Box 8)
    - Siegal, Barry S. 1942, Sept.-1944, Feb., 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Weckesser, Ella (Long) 1890, Mar.-1899, Apr., 1 folder (Box 8)
    - Whaley, Mirram (Weckesser) 1945, June-1982, Aug., 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Parapsychology
    - Case Studies, A-M, 1 folder (Box 8)
    - Case Studies, N-Z, 1 folder (Box 9)
    - Miscellany, 1961-1983, undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Business
    - 1930, July-1983, Feb., 3 folders (Box 9)
- Writings, 1920-1983 and undated, 3 boxes
  Divided into two categories: parapsychological and other writings. Within that arrangement, the papers are broken down into sub-categories that are chronologically and topically arranged. Included is information about the Rhines' writings and those of others.
  - Parapsychology
    - Anpsi Project,1950, 1 folder (Box 10)
    - Hidden Channels of the Mind (Box 10)
    - Spontaneous Psychic Experiences and the PSI Process, Excerpts,1978, 1 folder (Box 10)
    - Spontaneous Psychic Experiences and the PSI Process, Manuscript,1978, 1 folder (Box 10)
    - Articles, excerpts, undated, 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Notes, Miscellany
    - Rhine, Louisa E. ca. 1951-1970, 1 folder (Box 10)
    - Rhine, J. B. 1961-ca. 1977, undated, 1 folder (Box 10)
    - Journal of Parapsychology Index, 1937-1967, 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Critiques and Reviews
    - PSI: What Is It? Rhine, Louisa E., ca. 1975, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - Development of Parapsychology, 1979, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - The Elusive Science, Origins of Experimental Psychical Research Mauskoff, Seymour and Michael McVaugh, 1979-1981, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - The Invisible Picture, A Study of Psychic Experiences Rhine, Louisa E.,1979-1981, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - Enchanted Voyager, the Life of J. B. Rhine Brian, Denis, 1982, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - Miscellany,1929-1981, 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Other Writings:
    - Rhine, J. B., 1920-1959?, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - Rhine, Louisa E., 1920-1959?, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Rhine family,1928-1945, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - Our Life Together, 1937-1980, 1 folder (Box 11)
    - Interviews,1973-1980, 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches, Lectures, Articles
    - J. B. Rhine's Lectures on Personality, ca. 1941, 1 folder (Box 12)
    - Chronological File,1969-1983, undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Memorials,1980, 1 folder (Box 12)
- Genealogical Research, 1952-1979 and undated, 1 boxes
  Research about the Long and Weckesser families to whom Louisa Rhine was related, dating from 1702. Includes information about two works regarding the Weckesser family. Chronologically arranged.
  - Long, Weckesser Families,1952-1979, undated, 1 folder (Box 13)
- Miscellany, 1910-1981 and undated, 1 boxes
  Divided into two categories: 1) information relating to the Rhines' work and civic interests and 2) Louisa Rhine's psychical research notebooks and address books. Both categories are arranged chronologically.
  - Chronological File,1941-1981, undated, 1 folder (Box 13)
  - Notebooks,1910-1963, undated, 4 folders (Box 13)
- Pictures, 1934 and undated, 1 boxes
  Mainly Rhine family photographs, including those of J.B. Rhine, Louisa Rhine, and their children.
  - Chiefly 1934 and undated, 1 folder (Box 13)